I've still got a lot of years ahead of me
この想いを　消してしまうには
Kono omoi wo keshiteshimau niwa
To just erase these feelings?
まだ人生長いでしょ？
Mada jinsei nagai desho?
To just erase these feelings?
まだ人生長いでしょ？
I want to go back and finish
やり残してるコト
Yarinokoshiteru koto
The things that I've yet to finish.
やり直してみたいから
Yarinaoshite mitai kara
I was supposed to be chasing after my ongoing dream,
夢のつづき　追いかけていたはずなのに
Yume no tsuzuki oikaketeita hazu nanoni
Yet I faltered over others while walking this thin, winding path.
曲がりくねった　細い道　人につまずく
Magarikunetta hosoi michi hito ni tsumazuku
It's not that I want to return to those days.
あの頃みたいにって　戻りたい訳じゃないの
Ano koro mitainitte modoritai wake ja nai no
I'm searching for the sky I lost.
無くしてきた空を　探してる
Nakushitekita sora wo sagashiteru
Don't make that sad face, as if you've fallen victim.
わかってくれますように
Wakatte kuremasu youni
As if you want people to pity you.
犠牲になったような　悲しい顔はやめてよ
Gisei ni natta youna kanashii kao wa yameteyo
Tears aren't the end of your sins.
罪の最後は涙じゃないよ
Tsumi no saigo wa namida ja nai yo
You have to bear them painfully, forever.
ずっと苦しく背負ってくんだ
Zutto kurushiku seottekunda
Who are you waiting for in the maze of emotions,
出口見えない感情迷路に
Deguchi mienai kanjoumeiro ni
Where you can't even see the exit?
誰を待ってるの？
Dare wo matteruno?
I want to blurt it out more justly,
白いノートに綴ったように
Shiroi nooto ni tsuzutta youni
Just like how I wrote it in my white notebook.
もっと素直に吐き出したいよ
Motto sunao ni hakidashitai yo
What do you want to run from?
何から　逃れたいんだ
Nani kara nogaretainda
That thing called "reality"?
…現実ってやつ？
Genjitsu tte yatsu?
I just want to scream out,
叶えるために　生きてるんだって
Kanaeru tame ni ikiterundatte
"I'm only living to fulfill my wish." Can you hear me?
叫びたくなるよ　聞こえていますか？
Sakebitaku naru yo kikoeteimasuka?
I can't take the safe way out of everything.
無難になんて　やってられないから
Bunan ni nante yatterarenaikara
I don't even have a place to return to.
…帰る場所も無いの
Kaeru basho mo nai no
I'm always thankful for everyone's kindness,
優しさには　いつも感謝してる
Yasashisa ni wa itsumo kansha shiteru
That's why I want to become stronger. (I'm on the way)
だから強くなりたい(I'm on the the
(I'm on the way)
Dakara tsuyoku naritai (I'm on the way)
This is reminding me of the old days.
懐かしくなる
Natsukashiku naru
This pain is all right with me.
こんな痛みも歓迎じゃん
Konna itami mo kangei jan
We're almost at Dublith, Brother.
兄さん　そろそろダブリスに着くよ
Were you dreaming?
夢見てたの
Yeah.
ああ　あいつの夢だ
A dream about him.
We're finally here, aren't we?
とうとう来ちまったな
Yup.
うん
I hope the Master isn't home...
師匠　留守だといいな
Yeah...
うん
H-Hi...
どっ　どうも
It's been a while...
お久しぶりです
よく来た　大きくなったな
Welcome.
You've gotten bigger.
I-I'm going to shrink...
ち　縮む
Hi... It's me, Alphonse.
あの　アルフォンスです
It's been a while.
ごぶさたしてます
You've really  gotten bigger.
すごく大きくなったな
That's the first time I've been patted on the head since I became like this.
鎧になってから　初めて頭なでられた
Izumi, the Elric runts are here.
イズミ　エルリックのチビどもが来たぞ
Think you can get up?
起きられそうか
I'm fine.
大丈夫　今日は少し体調がいいから
I'm not feeling too bad today.
具合悪くて寝ていたんだ
I guess she was lying down because she wasn't feeling well.
Has her body not healed yet?
体　よくなってないのかな
You're one idiot of a disciple!
このバカ弟子が
What's this I hear about you becoming a dog of the military?!
軍の狗に成り下がったって
Master! W-Well... about this...
師匠　その　こっ　これは
Al! Look at how much you've grown!
アル　随分大きくなって
師匠もお変わりないよう
You haven't changed much either, Mast-
鍛え方が足りん
You've slacked on your training!
Oww...
痛てて
I thought you weren't feeling well?
具合悪かったんじゃないんですか
Forget about that! I'm out of bed like this because I heard you guys were here...
何を言う　お前たちが来たというからこうして
Don't push yourself.
無理しちゃダメだろ
You're worried about me, Dear?
心配してくれるのね　あなた
I don't know much about the Philosopher's Stone.
賢者の石についてはろくに知らん
興味ないからな
Because I'm not interested.
I see...
そうですか
We met an alchemist in Central who knew a lot about the stone, didn't we?
以前セントラルで
石にやたら詳しい錬金術師に会ったろ
What was he like?
どんな人です
I think his name was...
名前は　確か…
...Hohenheim.
ホーエンハイム
What's the matter?
どうした
生きてたんだ
So he's alive...
知り合いか
You know him?
He's our father.
父親です
So the one who left a long time ago...
昔　出ていったっていう
That bastard!
あんなヤツ
It's his fault Mom died.
あいつのせいで　母さんは死んだんだ
Because of him...
あいつのせいで
あら　どうしたの
Oh! What are you doing up so early?
こんな朝早く
Al said he needed to pee...
アルがおしっこって
Oh, so you were taking care of Al.
アルの面倒見てくれたのね
Thank you, Ed.
ありがとう　エド
Mom, where's Dad?
ねえ　お父さんは
出かけたわ
He left.
When's he coming back?
いつ帰って来るの
Tickle tickle tickle!
こちょこちょこちょ
すぐに帰って来るわよ
He'll be back in no time.
Hurry and finish your meal, now.
早く食べちゃいなさい
Mom...
お母さん
Mom.
母さん
Mom!
Mom!!!
お母さん
So... did Dad say anything about the stone?
あの　父さん　石について何か
長年の望みがもうすぐとか　嬉しそうに言ってたな
He looked happy, saying something about his wish from long ago will finally be coming true soon.
Ow!
痛っ
Time to eat!
飯にするぞ
はい
Okay...
You aren't going to eat, Al?
アルは食わんのか
N-No!
えっいえ　汽車の中でたくさん食べちゃって
I ate too much on the train...
Hey Al, tell them about how we witnessed childbirth over at Rush Valley!
ほら　アル
オレたちラッシュバレーで　出産に立ち会ったんだよな
そうそう　師匠
Oh yeah!
Master, we helped a baby being born!
僕たち赤ん坊を取り上げるの手伝ったんですよ
Idiot, that doesn't count as "helping".
バカ　手伝ったって言えるのかよ　あれで
I learned that people are born because everyone in the family works together,
家族が協力して　母親も命を懸けて
the mother risks her life, and because the person receives so many blessings from everyone.
みんなに祝福されて人間は生まれてくるんですね
That's right.
そうだよ　お前たちもそうやって生を受けた
That's how you two were given life, too.
Be proud that you were born.
自分の命に誇を持ちなさい
Brother.
兄さん
Hm?
Master hasn't changed at all, has she?
師匠変わらないね
Nope.
ああ　あのころから全然変わってない
She hasn't changed at all since we first met her.
Hang in there!
しっかりしろ
Bring over some more!
もっと持ってこい
It's going to collapse!
崩れるぞ
The levee's going to break! Run for high ground!
堤防が切れるぞ　高台に逃げろ
兄さん　見て
Brother, look!
Hey, it's dangerous!
おい　危ないぞ
これでしばらくはもつでしょう
This should last for a while.
W-Who are you?
あ　あんた何者だ
A passing housewife!
通りすがりの　主婦です
Will you please be our master, old lady?!
オレたちを弟子にしてよ　おばさん
Please, old lady!
お願いします　おばさん
ちょっと耳が遠くて聞こえなかったなぁ
I couldn't catch exactly what you said...
Mind repeating it?
もう一回言ってくれる
C-Correction!
て　訂正します
弟子にしてください　おねえさん
Please be our master, Miss!
No!
ダメ
Why not?!
なんで
I don't take students.
弟子は取らない主義
And besides, we're in the middle of a trip!
それに旅の途中だ
Please, accept us as your students!
お願い　弟子にして
God, you're so persistent!
しつこい
Do you even have permission from your parents?!
両親の許可は
The thing is... those boys don't have any parents.
あの　そいつら　親がいなくて
どうにも弱いね
I'm so soft when it comes to things like this...
Survive on your own!
二人だけで生き延びなさい
Huh?
That's the preliminary round.
それが仮修業
If you pass, we'll get to the real training.
うまくいったら本修業に入る
And you're not allowed to use alchemy during this preliminary round.
仮修業中は　錬金術使うの禁止ね
What?
「一は全 全は一」
"One is All, All is One."
１か月でその答えを見つけなさい
Find the answer to that within a month.
If you can't, I'm sending you back to Resembool.
答えが見つからない場合は
リゼンブールに送り返すからね
Later!
じゃあ
Huh?!
What the heck?!
なんじゃそりゃ
So hungry...
腹減った
ベッドで寝たいよ
I want to sleep in a bed, geez...
What part of this is alchemy training?!
これのどこが錬金術の修業なんだよ
So hungry...
腹減った
あいつら大丈夫かね
I wonder if those kids are all right?
経験に勝る知識なしってね
They say there's no substitute for real-life experience.
錬金術の肝の部分をたたき込むには
That is the best way to pound the courage portion of alchemy into them.
あの方法が一番なのよ
これで何も学べなかったら
If they don't learn anything from this,
it just means that's the extent of their talents.
所詮はそこまでの才能だってこと
弟子入りは諦めてもらう
They'll have to give up learning from me.
オレが心配してんのは
What I'm worried about is the safety of their lives.
あいつらの命の方だ
私の修業のときなんて
I was thrown out to Mt. Briggs in the middle of winter for a month during my training!
冬のブリッグス山に１か月ほうり込まれたわよ
お前と一般人を一緒にするな
Don't put yourself and ordinary people at the same level.
There's so much to eat on that island; they'll live.
あの島は食料豊富だし
死にゃしないわよ
やった
We did it!
どうやって食べるのこれ
How do we eat this?
Hmm... We cut it apart.
スパッと
Cut it apart...
I don't want to do it!
やだよ　兄さんがやってよ
You do it!
I did the catching; you do the killing.
オレ　捕まえるの専門
面倒なこといっつも押しつけて
You always try to make me do all the things you don't want to do!
ああ　待て
Get back here!!!
子ギツネ
Baby foxes...
肉はやめて魚にしよう
Forget meat... let's try for some fish.
ってどうやって魚とるんだよ
How do we catch one?!
竿も糸も針もねぇんだぞ
We don't have a rod, line, or a needle!
No food, no fire, no nothing...
食べ物ない　火もない
なんにもない
言うなよ
Don't say that!
もう
Geez!
何すんだよ　兄さん
What was that for, Brother?!
Brother?
兄さん
うおぉ　酸っぺぇ
Sour!
I'm... alive.
オレ　生きてるんだ
アリを食って　生きてる
Eating ants and living.
命を食って　生きてる
Eating life and living.
生きてる
Living...
オレたちは死なない
We're not going to die here!
うん
Right!
ごめんな
Sorry about this...
You're almost there, Brother.
兄さん　もうちょっとだよ
We did it!
うわ　やった
明日で１か月か
Looks like tomorrow's the end of the month...
ねえ兄さん　「一は全 全は一」の答えって見つかった
Hey Brother,
did you ever find the answer to "One is All, All is One"?
ずっと考えているけどなんとなくしか分からないよ
I've been thinking about it for the longest time, but I only kind of understand it.
I'm not positive, but...
確信はねぇけど
ほら　腹減ってへろへろだった時アリ食ったろ
Remember when I ate ants when we were starving and out of it?
そうだっけ
You did?
うん　食ったんだよ
Yep, I did.
They were so sour.
すげぇ酸っぱかった
で　考えたんだ
Then, a thought came to my mind.
もし食わないでオレが死んだら
If I hadn't eaten them and eventually died,
キツネやアリに食われる
foxes and ants would eat me.
土に還って草になる
I'd return to the soil and become grass.
それをウサギが食べる
And that's what a rabbit would eat.
食物連鎖だね
The food chain, right?
ああ　それだけじゃない
Yeah.
But that's not all.
この島だって　大昔は海の底だったかもしれない
Even this island could have been underwater in the ancient times.
And tens of thousands of years in the future,
it could be a summit of a mountain.
何万年もしたら　山のてっぺんになってるかもしれない
Everything is connected?
何もかもつながってる
すべては目に見えない
Everything is within a large stream that can't be seen.
大きな流れの中にあるんだ
それを宇宙っていうのか
I don't know if that stream should be called the universe or the world,
世界っていうのかは分かんないけど
そんなでっかいものからすりゃ
but from the point of view of something that big, you and I are like ants.
オレもアルもアリみたいなもんさ
流れの中の小さな一つ
A small individual within a stream.
We're just "one" within the "all".
「全」の中の「一」にすぎない
だけど　その小さな「一」が集まって
But only when those "ones" gather together, can an "all" exist.
「全」が 存在できる
その世は想像もできない…
約束の日だ
It's the promised day.
「一は全　全は一」の答えを聞こう
Let's hear your answer to "One is All, All is One".
「全」は世界
"All" is the world!
And "One" is me!
「一」はオレ
よろしい　本修業に移ろう
Good! We can start the real training now.
しゃ
All right!
錬成陣の基本は　円の力
A basis of a transmutation circle is the power of the circle.
The circle displays the circulation of power,
円は力の循環を示し
そこに構築式を描くことで
and by sketching the construction symbol in it,
it becomes possible to activate its power.
力の発動が可能になる
これも力の循環
This is also a circulation of power.
It's best to experience it for yourself.
体感するのがいちばんいい
さてと　昼ご飯の支度ができるまで復習しておくように
Now...
Review it until lunch is ready!
ええっと　「円は 力の循環を示し
Okay, so...
The circle displays the circulation of power,
and by sketching the construction symbol in it,
it becomes possible to activate its power.
そこに構築式を描くことで
力の発動が可能になる」
でも 師匠は手のひらを合わせただけで錬成してましたよね
But you were transmuting by just slapping your palms together, weren't you, Master?
構築式は書かなくていいんですか
Do you not need to sketch the construction symbols?
私自身が構築式みたいなものかな
I am like a construction symbol.
What do you have to do in order to do that?
どうやったらできるんです
真理にたどりつけば　できるようになるかもね
You might be able to do it if you ever reach the truth.
師匠も真理を
Master has also seen the truth...
And? What did you want to talk to me about?
で　話というのはなんだ
えっと
W-Well...
やはり構築式なしに錬成できるか
As I thought, you can transmute without a construction symbol!
Additionally, Alphonse is an empty suit of armor!
加えてアルフォンスは空っぽの鎧
You've got automails for an arm and leg!
お前は片手片足が機械鎧
How did you know, Master?!
師匠　どうして
それくらい手合わせすれば分かる
I can tell from just sparring with you!
You... saw it, didn't you?
お前あれを見たな
見たな
Am I right?!
Y-Yes, ma'am!
はい
師弟そろってしょうもない
Both master and pupil, making the same stupid decisions.
師匠は　あれを見たから
Master, you...
Because you saw that thing...
私たち夫婦にはなかなか子供ができなくてね
We had a hard time conceiving a child.
ようやくできたっていうのに
Just when we thought we were having a baby, I fell ill.
私が病気になっちまって
私たちの子は
Because of that, our child wasn't born into this world alive.
生きてこの世に生まれることができなかった
だから
So...
禁忌を犯したんだ
...I committed taboo.
お陰で　中をあっちこっち持っていかれた
Thanks to that, all sorts of organs were taken from me.
本当に大バカ者だよ
I'm such an idiot.
もっと早く話しとくべきだったね
I should have told you sooner.
辛かったろう
It must have been tough.
い　いいえ
N-No!
自分でやったことですし
It's something we did to ourselves.
辛いとかそういう気持ちは
We don't particularly find it tough...
I think about what to eat when I get my body back.
体を取り戻したら　何食べようとか
It's quite the opposite; it's more of an anticipation!
逆に楽しみなんですよ
ねっ　兄さん
Right, Brother?
おう　そうだよな
Yeah!
That's exactly it!
このバカタレが
You morons...
無理しなくていい
No need to force yourselves.
すみません
Forgive us...
ごめんなさい
We're sorry...
すみません
Forgive us...
ごめんなさい
We're sorry...
すみません
Forgive us...
ごめんなさい
We're sorry...
すみません
Forgive us...
この世は想像もできない
This world is flowing while abiding by a great rule that's unimaginable.
大きな法則に従って流れているんだ
その流れを知り
Learning about that flow,
breaking it down, and rebuilding it.
分析して　再構築する
That's what alchemy's all about.
それが錬金術
そして　生きることでもある
And it's also what living is about, too.
The basics of alchemy, breaking
something down and rebuilding it...
錬金術の基本　分解再構築っていうのは
食物連鎖そっくりだね
That's almost like the food chain.
If you eat a rabbit, you break down
its meat and rebuild it into your own body.
ウサギを食べたら　その肉を分解して
自分の体に再構築する
ウサギだって　食べた草を自分の体に再構築している
And even that rabbit rebuilds
the grass it ate into its own body.
錬金術っていうのは　命そのものなんだ
Alchemy is life itself.
Say, the sky we saw that day, the scarlet sky.
あの日見た空　茜色の空を
Ano hi mita sora akaneiro no sora wo
Do you remember it from that day?
ねえ　君は覚えていますか
Nee kimi wa oboeteimasuka
We made a promise and a vow while the early summer wind circled us.
約束　契り　初夏の風が包む
Yakusoku chigiri shoka no kaze ga tsutsumu
And we clung close together.
二人　寄り添った
Futari yorisotta
Your forced smile
無理な笑顔の裏
Muri na egao no ura
Holds elongated shadows.
伸びた影をかくまう
Nobita kage wo kakumau
I pretend not to notice and continue on.
だから　気づかぬふり　再生を選ぶ
Dakara kizukanu furi saisei wo erabu
All the while waiting for you to deliver some news at the table.
テーブルの上の　震えない知らせ　待ち続けて
Teeburu no ue no furuenai shirase machitsuzukete
Empty nights, mornings that will never arrive,
空白の夜も　来るはずのない朝も
Kuuhaku no yoru mo kuru hazu no nai asa mo
I could see them from a mile away.
全部わかってたんだ
Zenbu wakattetanda
Say, the sky we saw that day, the scarlet sky.
あの日見た空　茜色の空を
Ano hi mita sora akaneiro no sora wo
I'm sure you'll remember it one day.
ねえ　 いつか思い出すでしょう
Nee itsuka omoidasu deshou
While holding the promise we couldn't keep,
果たせなかった　約束を抱いて
Hatasenakatta yakusoku wo idaite
We take our first steps down our own paths.
二人　歩き出す
Futari arukidasu
日本語字幕仕上げ：FAYFAY
己の欲望を楽しむ者
A man who enjoys his own desires.
名はグリード
His name is Greed.
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
敵か味方か
Whether he be friend or foe, the figure that stands before Ed and Al is a body made for fighting.
エドたちの前に立つその姿は
戦うためにあるがごとき異形
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
FULLMETAL ALCHEMIST
第十三話　ダブリスの獣たち
Episode 13, Beasts of Dublith.
強き者　その姿を現す
A powerful figure appears before the two.
人体錬成…
やったのか、やらなかったのか
私の理論は完璧でしたか？
お嬢様は？！
荒川弘の名作、盲目の錬金術師
待望のアニメーション化
人は、その『業』故に、咎人となるのか…
鋼の錬金術師
Fullmetal Alchemist
DVD&Blu-ray Disk 第1巻
8月26日発売